<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth exalted and deceit abased, or, A discovery of the false Christs and false prophets spoken of in the 7th and 24th chapters of Matthew shewing also when they came, and how they may be known, to the end that all honest people may be aware of them ... : also, here is something concerning the practice and doctrine of the</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F512A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18557</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12874169</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12874169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94811</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40954)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94811)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 981:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth exalted and deceit abased, or, A discovery of the false Christs and false prophets spoken of in the 7th and 24th chapters of Matthew shewing also when they came, and how they may be known, to the end that all honest people may be aware of them ... : also, here is something concerning the practice and doctrine of the</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Farnworth. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94811:1"/>
            <p>TRUTH EXALTED AND Deceit abaſed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A diſcovery of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſpoken of in the 7th. and 24th. Chapters of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> ſhewing alſo when they came, and how they may be known, to the end that all honeſt people may be aware of them, for they have had a long reign, but God is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering them, and bringing people off from them, to the truth and true Goſpel Miniſtry and worſhip, which was before their coming, aforementioned.</p>
            <p>Alſo here is ſomething concerning the practice and Doctrine of the true Goſpel-Miniſters according to the Scriptures, and the Doctrine of the falſe Prophets compared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and wherein they differ, as may be ſeen to them that read with a right underſtanding: Likewiſe here is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning laying on of hands according to the Scriptures, and concerning ſinging, and the righteous mans falling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As alſo Prayer, and concerning free grace, and concerning Faith according to the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe here is ſeverall Queries about the riſe of Tythes ſince the Apoſtacy, or coming of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, and concerning the foundation of the Engliſh Church (though in the time of Popery called the Holy Church) with ſeverall alterations and changes therein, very uſefull to be taken into due conſideration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the foundation of God ſtands ſure, having this Seal, <hi>the Lord knoweth them that are his,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Eagle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94811:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94811:2"/>
            <head>TRVTH EXALTED AND Deceit abaſed, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there was ſomething ſaid by the Preiſt of which about falſe Prophets, &amp;c. and it is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall outcry in the world amongſt Teachers and Profeſſors concerning falſe Chriſts and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come and deceive many, and the cry is that they are but now come, and that theſe are the laſt times of which Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come, and ſay they; now they are come according to the Prophecy of Chriſt and ſaying in the Scriptures, where he hath foretold of them, and ſaid they ſhould come, as in <hi>Matthew</hi> the twenty ſeventh, and twenty fourth Chapters. To which it is anſwered as hereafter followeth, in reference to the ſaying and Prophecy of Chriſt, that ſpeaks and foretells of the coming of the falſe Chriſts and the falſe Prophets (as aforeſaid) It is anſwered that ſuch as ſay they are but come now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey ſpeak ignorantly and without underſtanding, and they are ignorant of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94811:3"/>Scriptures, and the comming of them and their long reigne, that ſo affirme, who ſay, they are but now come, be they Preiſts, Parſons, Rectors, Doctors, Elders, and Teachers or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of what ſort ſo ever; for as Chriſt told of falſe Prophets <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. So he alſo ſaid that by their fruits they ſhould be known ver. 16.20. of the ſame Chapter: And then ſaid Chriſt unto his Diſciples beware of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly are ravening Wolves, for by their fruits ye ſhall know them, it is to be obſerved that Chriſt ſpakes this unto his Diſciples whilſt he were perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally preſent with them, and that he bad his Diſciples then to beware of the ſaid falſe Prophets, and alſo gave them a rule or marke by which they might know them (as aforeſaid) and in <hi>Mat.</hi> ver. 11. Chriſt propheſied or foretold that many falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe, and not onely ſo, but alſo they ſhould deceive many, and ſaith Chriſt in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, &amp;c. in ſo much that if it were poſſible they ſhould deceived the very elect (but it is not poſſible that the elect ſhould be deceived by them) yet Chriſt hath told his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. that falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe and deceive many, and that they would deliver up the Saints or Diſciples and followers of the true chriſt to be afflicted, and that they ſhould kill them, &amp;c. then ſhould iniquity abound; and that prophecy of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath been fullfilled in a great abundant meaſure, on the falſe Prophets part, together with ſuch as have been ſeduced by them, and many of the Saints and ſervants of Chriſt have by the means of the falſe Prophets been impriſoned, killed, hated and delivered up to be perſecuted, ſcourged and afflicted, ſuch hard meaſure hath and doth the Saints and ſervants of Chriſt mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with, by reaſon of the falſe Prophets and them that they have deceived. Therefore the falſe Prophets do and have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a deavouring or wolviſh nature, though they have been like wolves hid in ſheeps clothing, and covered with a pretence of godlineſſe, yet formerly they have appeared and ſtill doe appear in a devouring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure, more like unto Dogs and Wolves (to rend and tear t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lambs and Sheep of Chriſt) than good Shepheards to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſerve or guide and feed the Flock
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94811:3"/>of God 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. but with force and cruelty have the falſe Prophets againſt them appeared, and have neither ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Diſeaſed, nor healed that which was ſick, neither have they bound up that which was broken, nor brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that which was driven away, neither have they ſought that which was loſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but with force and with cruelty have they ruled like ſuch that the Lord is againſt, who eat the fat and cloth them with the wool, but feed not the flock; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeek to perſecute and kill them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.3, 4. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the aforeſaid prophecy of Chriſt is in a great and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant meaſure fulfilled; And again ſaith Chriſt Ieſus our Lord in <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.22. falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, if it were poſſible, the very elect; but ſaith he, take ye heed, behold I have foretold you, ver. 23. who was it that he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, was it not his Diſciples that he foretold (as aforeſaid) yea and moreover Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Saviour declared and foretold of the coming of falſe Chriſts and falls Prophets (as aforementioned) and ſaid he then, this generation ſhall not paſs till all theſe things be fulfilled or done, as may be read, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.30. did Chriſt Ieſus ſay to his Diſciples whilſt he was perſonally preſent with them, that falſe Prophets (and as aforeſaid) ſhould come, and did he whilſt perſonally preſent with his Diſciples bid them beware of them, and did he alſo affirme, that the generation then preſent ſhould not paſs away till thoſe things ſpoken of in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. and <hi>Mar.</hi> 13, ſhould be done, amongſt which things ſpoken of was the falſe Prophets riſe and coming, how is it then that Prieſts and Profeſſors are ſo ignorant of the Scriptures, and cry they are but now come, what will ye be lyars of Chriſt, of the Scriptures, and of the Doctrine of the holy Apoſtles? are ye reſolved to ſeek to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, and withſtand them all? be not ſo impudent and wicked, hath not Chriſt ſaid (as aforementioned) that falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe and come, by whoſe means many ſhould be deceived? And did not Chriſt ſay, that generation then preſent ſhould not paſs till they came, or thoſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the paſſing way of that genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be done, and is this the generation of men (that generation) which were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94811:4"/>perſonally preſent then; though the evill Spirit of error doe rule in a great number of the perſons, who are of the ſeed of evill doers, in this ſinfull (and ſin contending for) genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet there hath been many generations ſince Chriſt ſaid, falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhould come; And that that generation then preſent (whilſt Chriſt were perſonally with them) ſhould not paſs till thoſe things ſhould be done; how is it then that Prieſts and Pofeſſors are ſo ignorant of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to try they are but come now, and that theſe are the laſt times of which Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come: Obſerve, Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples while perſonally preſent with them, falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould come, and deceive many <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. (as aforeſaid) and he alſo ſaid that generation ſhould not paſs, till thoſe things ſhould be done, this Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples and friends, whilſt perſonally preſent with them; and ſaid beware of them, for many ſhalbe deceived by them; and you ſhall be delivered up to be afflicted, and ye ſhall be killed and hated of all nations for my names ſake, and as Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come, <hi>Iohn</hi> in his time (or in that generation before it was paſſed) ſaid they were come, and moreover he ſaid that was the laſt time, in which it was ſaid they ſhould come, for ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> in the 1. Epiſtle 2. Chapter 18, 19. ver. Little children it is the laſt time; and as you have heard that Anti-Chriſt ſhould come, even now are there many falſe Chriſts, or Anti-Chriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt time, here they were come, yet prieſts and profeſſors are ſo ignorant of the Scripture, that they cry out now they are come, and they are come, but now when they came before the deceaſe of the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi> many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ſince, yea ſaith he, they went out from us, but they were not of us, for if they had been of us, no doubt but they would have continued with us, but they went out that they might be made manifeſt, they were not all of us, ver. 19. And as Chriſt had foretold his Diſciples of the coming of thoſe falſe Chriſts, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how they would deceive many, ſaith he, goe not forth (or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t after them, but rather abide within) ſo when they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap> me, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid and declared then, that they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94811:4"/>were not come in his time, and he writ to the faithfull to keep to the anointing within, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20, 27. And here <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſtle agreed with Chriſts Doctrine, and moreover as <hi>Iohn</hi> had told that the falſe Chriſts or Anti-Chriſts were come, and exhorted the faithfull to keep to the anointing within, he alſo ſaid that the falſe Prophets were come, and were already gone out into the world, beloved ſaid he, to them that kept to the anointing within them, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.27. and kept the commandements of Chriſt, and knew that he abode in them, and that they abode in him, becauſe he had given them of his Spirit, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.23, 24. yea, and ſuch as had overcome the Devil, the wicked one, and had the word of God abiding in them, ver. 13.14. who were of God and not of the world, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19. who being of God knew the Son of God to be come, and ſaid he had given them an underſtanding to know him that is true, and then they were in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.20. they did not deny Chriſt to be within who were in him and he in them, neither were they of the world but of God, and ſuch <hi>Iohn</hi> writ unto to try the Spirits; he did not write unto the world (nor hireling Prieſts) to try the Spirits, take notice of that, but he writ to them that were not of the world but of God, and were in Chriſt, and owned and profeſſed Chriſt to be in them (as aforeſaid) to ſuch he writ to try the Spirits, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beloved beleeve not every Spirit, but try the Spirits, whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. (marke) many falſe Prophets (ſaith he) are gone out into the world, then they were come long before this time, and ſince then they have had a long reign, and now is God diſcovering them, and bringing people off from them; Chriſt ſaid they ſhould come, <hi>viz.</hi> falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and falſe Chriſts, and <hi>John</hi> ſaw they were come and went out from them, and was not that, which inwardly ravened from the Spirit of God into the Apoſtacy, the ground which the falſe Prophets roſe out of, and did not they that turned from the truth, and abode not in it, joyn together with the Beaſt to make war with the Saints? and did not ſuch turne againſt the Saints as ran a whoring from that of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and did not they make war with the Saints and overcome them and did not the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94811:5"/>deceive and ſeduce Nations, and Kindreds, Languages, and multitudes, and ſet up the Image or worſhip of the Beaſt, and did not all that dwelt upon the earth goe out after them, and worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, but the elect whoſe names are written in the Lambes book of life, ſlaine from the foundation of the world, and muſt not they that worſhip the Beaſt and his Image be plagued and tormented, as may be read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. Chriſt ſaid, <hi>falſe Prophets ſhould come and deceive many,</hi> yea, if it were poſſible the very elect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 <hi>John</hi> ſaw they were come and gone out into the world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18, 19. and in the <hi>Rev. John</hi> ſpeaks of the Beaſt and falſe Prophet joyning together, and how they had prevailed, but the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet are to be caſt together into the lake of fire and brimſtone, and muſt be tormented day and night for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10. here he hath declared their puniſhment to be everlaſting, <hi>John</hi> ſaw that all the world wondered after the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3. and they worſhipped the Beaſt, ſaying who is like unto the Beaſt, who is able to make war with him, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. when he had made war with the Saints, and had overcome them, was not power given him over all Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and did not the Beaſt ſo prevaile when he had made war with the Saints and overcome them, that he ſet up in the time of Apoſtacy, when he had dominion in <hi>England,</hi> in and through the Pope, Schools, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, called Vniverſities, to fit and make miniſters for himſelf, and was not all conſtrained to worſhip that which vvas ſet up in the Apoſtacy, but ſuch as had their names written in the Lambs Book of life, who could not worſhip the Beaſt and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Image, but rather chooſed to ſuffer, and he cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to receive a marke in their right hand, and in their foreheads, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16. and was not Cathedralls and Pariſh Churches, ſo called, with the reſt of the ſuperſtition their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, and ſprinkling infants with the marke in the forehead, ſet up in the time of Apoſtacy; and did not the Pope by his decretall Epiſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cauſe Tithes to be paid to the Parſons and Rectors of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and did they not ſo become <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> and ſo into paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall rights, ſo called, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e from, See <hi>Cookes</hi> 2. part Inſtitutes <hi>fol.</hi> 641.642. was not that the ground and riſe of Tithes in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94811:5"/>to the Pariſh Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Did not the Pope create thoſe names of Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the time of Apoſtacy, with a great number more of them, and was not thoſe names that he created of the number of the Beaſt, which is ſaid to be the number of a man, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 13.18. and is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe names which the Pope created yet upheld and ſtood in, as Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And doe they not hold Tithes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch denominations; if ſo, is not that an evident demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they are yet in the Popes creation and of his ſucceſſion, and as <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelation ſpeaketh of the Beaſt and his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that took place in the Apoſtacy, doth he not ſpeak of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Beaſt, that had life given to it in ſeverall appearances, was not thoſe Images of the Beaſt ſeverall inventions, and ſet formes of worſhip, which had life given to them by nationall Laws, or elſe by force of the ſaid Laws, people were bound to the Image and worſhip of the Beaſt, or for their refuſall they ſuffered deeply, and was not the Maſs Book an invention of the Beaſt and one of his images or forme of worſhip ſet up in <hi>England</hi> as well as other place; And was not people in <hi>England</hi> a long time bound to the Maſs. Book, or that image and worſhip of the Beaſt, and when that was diſcovered or denyed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. was not the Common Prayer book ſet up in the ſtead thereof, See the Statute of the 1. and 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.1. and was not that another invention or image of the Beaſt, and ſet forme of worſhip which had life given to it by a Law, though not much differing from the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the Maſs book, and was not the life of that image or worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> the Common Prayer book taken away againe, by a Law of Queen <hi>Maries,</hi> and did not ſhe by the ſame Law give life againe to the former image of the Beaſt, that is to ſay the Maſs book, or that forme of worſhip which was in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8. See <hi>Seſſio ſecunda Anno Mariae primo Cap.</hi> 2. and 3. And did not <hi>Elizabeth</hi> who the next after ſucceeded <hi>Mary,</hi> repeale thoſe Laws that gave life to the Maſs book, and did ſhe not ſet up the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er book againe, and give life to the ſame by a Law: or thereby compell and binde people to the performance and worſhip of that image and uniforme worſhip ſet up by <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 6. <hi>viz.</hi> the Common Prayer book; See the Statute of the 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. And was not the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94811:6"/>ſame worſhip cried up as the true Chriſtian Proteſtant Religion, and confirmed by ſeverall Parliaments, or ſtood in force during the times of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> untill it was diſcovered, and the life of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the Common Prayer book was taken away in the time of the late war, or the ſaid Common Prayer book was by Act of Parliament diſanulled; And what was the next unto that, but a Directory, and was it not fetcht out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſet up to be obſerved, and what muſt be next the Common Prayer book againe, or ſomething of the like nature, drawn up into an uniforme, or would not the Patiſh Prieſts, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have it to be ſo, elſe what meaneth the pleading of ſome of them for the Common Prayer book, or the like uniforme worſhip, may it not be well ſaid that people and nations are as waters toſſed to and fro, that have been and are ſo unſetled about their Religion, ſince the coming of the falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets in the time of Apoſtacy, hath not the Beaſt, which <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelations ſpeaks of, made war with the Saints, ever ſince the time of the coming of the falſe Prophets ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. or ſince the time that Apoſtacy took place, and hath he not, to wit, the Beaſt overcome the Saints by perſecuting and putting them to death, but is not the promiſe that the Lamb ſhall overcome, and them that are with him, who are called and choſen, and faithfull, and muſt not the everlaſting Goſpel be preached againe to all Nations, and Kindreds, and Peoples? hath not the Beaſt long reigned in Apoſtacy, and did not <hi>Iohn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his deceaſe foreſee it, and declared that the Beaſt had power given over all Kindreds and Tongues, and Nations, and hath not all that dwell upon the earth worſhipped the Beaſt but them, that is to ſay the elect, whoſe names are written in the book of life of the Lamb ſlaine from the foundation of the world, and is not the prophecy of <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelations, ſince the Apoſtacy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the aforeſaid falſe Prophets, largely fulfilled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7.8. And hath not the Beaſt, according to that prophecy, long had power over Tongues, and to have power over Tongues, hath it not been to order them by Maſters of Art, Batchelors of Art, Vice-Chancelors over Colledges and others, ſuch as are of the number of the names of the Beaſt, who are expert in the deceit,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94811:6"/>or Magick Art, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is not thoſe Tongues that are ſo ordered which the Beaſt hath power over as aforeſaid, learned at Colledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are not thoſe Colledges called by names given in the time of Popery, and was they not then erected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is not the Beaſt yet worſhipped, and muſt they not drink of the wine of the wrath of God poured out without mixture, into the Cup of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and be tormented night and day, who worſhip the Beaſt and his image, and whoſoever receiveth the marke of his name, as ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelations, Chap. 14.9,10, 11. What is the whores Cup of fornication, and the great whore that hath long ſitten upon the waters, with which whore the Kings of the earth have committed fornication, in which the blood of the Martyrs is found See <hi>Reve.</hi> 17. and read with underſtanding, are not the waters where the whore ſitteth there ſpoken of, declared to be peoples and multitudes, and Nations, and Tongues ver. 15. doth the whore ſit upon Tongues, what upon Greek, Latine and Hebrew, Schollers at Univerſities, or Colledges, now and ever ſince they were erected or ſet up in the time of Apoſtacy, after the coming of the falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw were come, and have they not ſince then deceived the Nations; and are they no more ſetled then waters, or how ſhould it be otherwiſe whilſt they erre from the true Spirit, and follow their own inventions; but God is now bringing and hath brought many people out of the waters to the Rock Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and is building them together in him, upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, in whom all the building fitly framed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether groweth to an holy Temple in the Lord, For an habitation of God through the Spirit, <hi>Eph,</hi> 2.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. And now is the Lord bringing people to the true ſpirituall worſhip againe according to the Scriptures, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23, 24. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.3. (which was before the Apoſtacy) at which the falſe Prophets that hath long rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned in the time of Apoſtacy are greatly offended, but it is but that the Scriptures may be fulfilled which ſaith, evill men and ſeducers, ſhall waxe worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. The true Chriſtians owned and profeſſed Chriſt Jeſus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, before the Apoſtacy, and did not deny Revelation but ſince the Apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and Antichriſtians denyeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94811:7"/>the true Chriſt to have an inbeing in his people, and are offended at ſuch as own revelation, and the true Chriſt to be within accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures; The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> not of men neither by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead, did affirme and certify to the Brethren before the Apoſtacy, that the Goſpel which was preached of him, was not after man, nor received of man, neither was he taught it, but by the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1.11, 12. he did not deny revelation, as the falſe Prophets doe, but ſaid, when it pleaſed God, who called me by his grace to reveale his Son in me, that I might preach him among the Heathen, immediatly I conferred not with fleſh and blood, but went into <hi>Arabia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17. here this true Goſpel Miniſter neither denyed revelation nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the Son, but witneſſed that God had revealed him unto him, and that within as aforeſaid, but the falſe Apoſtles and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets deny both revelation and Chriſt to be within, the true A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaid he was not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, which Goſpel he affirmed and declared to be the power of God unto ſalvation, unto every one that beleeveth, and furthermore he hath affirmed that therein, <hi>viz.</hi> the Goſpel of Chriſt which is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God as aforeſaid, is the righteouſneſs of God revealed from faith to faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, 17. here againe the true Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter before the Apoſtacy owned revelation, and did not ſay it was ceaſed, neither was he aſhamed of that Goſpel of Chriſt, namely the power of God, wherein the righteouſneſs of God is revealed from faith to faith as aforeſaid, and the ſame Apoſtle before the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy commanded, that if any man, yea or an Angel from Heaven preach any other Goſpel than that, which he with the reſt had prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched, to let ſuch beholden accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8, 9. but ſince the apoſtacy the falſe Apoſtles or Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt; together with the falſe Prophets who deny revelation and ſay its ceaſed, they preach a contrary Goſpel to that which the true Apoſtles preached, where in the righteouſneſs of God as aforeſaid, is from faith to faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; therefore the ſaid falſe Apoſtles or Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, together with the falſe Prophets are held accurſed; The true Goſpel Miniſter in whom Chriſt was revealed, in preaching to the Gentiles before the Apoſtacy, where he ſpeaks of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94811:7"/>which God would make known among the Gentiles, he hath declared it, to be Chriſt in them the hope of glory, whom ſaith he we preach and teach, <hi>&amp;c. Col.</hi> 1.27.28. did not the true Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Miniſters in ſo preaching preach Chriſt within as aforeſaid; and doe not the falſe Prophets ſince the Apoſtacy deny ſuch a doctrine: The true Goſpel Miniſters before the Apoſtacy prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpel, with the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. but ſince the Apoſtacy the falſe Prophets ſeeks to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the office of the Holy Ghoſt, and are highly offended at them now, that preach the Goſpel againe, with the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven; the true Goſpel-Miniſter before the Apoſtacy, was called and ſent to turne people from the darkneſs to the light, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.16, 17, 18. and ſo from the power of Satan to the power of God, but in the Apoſtacy and enmity the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets are againſt the true light, and thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oppoſite both endeavouring to keep all they can, for owning the light and joyning to the ſame, and they alſo labour by their wiles, ſlights and cunning craftineſs to ſeduce, and as much as in them lyeth to turne people from the true light to the darkneſs againe, and ſo from the power of God to the power of Satan, but now they are known, for the day is dawned, and the day Star a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſen in the hearts of many, and the day declareth every mans works of what ſort they are, therefore as this is read with a right underſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let them that ſo read, take notice who the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets are, and of them hereafter be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Revelation and the Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreover in the Primitive time before the Apoſtacy or coming of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw were come, as aforementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the true Goſpel-Miniſters were ſo far from denying Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, That they ſaid, No man knoweth the things of God but by the ſpirit of God, which revealeth the deep things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11. And they alſo declared and ſaid that they had not received the Spirit of the world, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94811:8"/>the Spirit of God, that they might know the things, that were freely given them of God, ver. 12. and if no man know the things of God, but by the Spirit of God, which revealeth the deep things of God, then to deny Revelations and ſay they are ceaſed, Is not that to deny the office and work of the Spirit of God, and ſay it is ceaſed; and doe not they that ſay ſo plainly ſhew that they are falſe Prophets, and falſe Apoſtles, or Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, and doe not ſuch alſo deny the true Apoſtles Doctrine, and ſhew that they are ignorant, and without the true Spirit guiding them to ſpeak, and that they know not the things of the Spirit of God, who deny Revelation the office and work of the Spirit, to reveale and make known the things of God as aforeſaid, without which Spirit of God or a meaſure thereof, no man can know the things of God, as the true Apoſtles hath ſaid.</p>
               <p>The true Goſpel-Miniſter before the Apoſtacy, declared and ſaid that if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. but the falſe Prophets or Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt ſince the Apoſtacy, deny that any man ſhould have the Spirit of Chriſt, and they doe not onely declare thereby that they are none of his Miniſters, but alſo that Chriſt hath no true Diſciples or Subjects, Therefore they that deny the Spirit of Chriſt they muſt needs be falſe Prophets, and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, or the Devils Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, note ſuch and take it for granted, they are the enemies of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The true Goſpel-Miniſters and Saints in Chriſt Jeſus, before the Apoſtacy declared and affirmed, that they had received the Spirit of God, whereby they knew the things, that were freely given them of God, and by the ſame Spirit they knew, that they were children of God and joynt heirs with Chriſt, and could by divine right ſay it, the Spirit of God alſo witneſſing, with their Spirit that it was true, and thereby, <hi>viz.</hi> by the Spirit which they had received of God, or by the Spirit of his Son, which he had ſent into their hearts, they could cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14, 15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Gal,</hi> 4, 6. But ſince the Apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt declares and affirms, that it is preſumption or blaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemy, for any to affirme now, that they have the Spirit of God, and know thereby the things, which are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94811:8"/>freely given them or God, and to ſay that they are the children of God, and joynt heirs with Chriſt, and that they have the Spirit of God, as an evidence bearing witneſs with their Spirit, according to the Scriptures, that it is ſo; and that God hath ſent the ſpirit of his Son into their hearts, whereby they cry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Abba</hi> Father, and can ſo call him by divine right, according to the Scriptures, as the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus formerly did; This the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt calleth preſumption, deluſion and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, therefore note them, and as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.20. <hi>by their fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The true Apoſtle and Miniſter of Chriſt before the Apoſtacy exhorted or counſelled the people to walk in the ſpirit, to the end that they might not fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that live in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, as the true Goſpel Miniſter before the Apoſtacy hath ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8. and the fruits of the fleſh are manifeſt ſaith he, which are theſe, See <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. and they which doe ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God, as the true Goſpel-Miniſter hath ſaid, and as may be read, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5, 6. But ſince the Apoſtacy the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, they deny the Spirit of truth, and labours to keep people from walking in the Spirit of God, to the end that they may fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, and that they may live in the fleſh, and be kept but of the Spirit, leaſt they ſhould pleaſe God, and ſo for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and ſtrengthning Satans intereſt in people they are, and labours to keep people in ſin, and to pleade for the ſame, that they may live in the fleſh, and bring forth the works thereof, to the end that they may be fitted for Satan, and be kept out of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; Therefore it is high time for people, that hath any regard to the glory of God and of their ſouls good to look about them, and not any longer follow the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, that hath had ſuch a long reigne, and are expert in the work of deceiving.</p>
               <p>The true Goſpel-Miniſter before the Apoſtacy counſelled peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he miniſtred unto, not onely to walk in the Spirit, that they might not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh, but alſo that through the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they might mortify the deeds of the body, to the end that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94811:9"/>might live unto God, and bring forth the fruits of the Spirit and ſo glorify him: But ſince the apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Anti-Chriſt, they labour to keep people from the Spirit, leaſt the deeds of the fleſh ſhould be mortified, and therefore they labour to keep them out of the Spirit of truth, leaſt they ſhould by it be led out of deceit and into the truth, to live to the praiſe and glory of God as aforeſaid, alſo ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13, 14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24. For if they ſhould walk in the Spirit, and bring forth fruit unto God, and dye to the world; Satan would looſe his hold, and his intereſt in people would ceaſe and come to an end; Therefore that he may uphold a kingdome of ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, covered over with a pretence of godlineſs in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ſits the falſe Prophets and ſeducers to labour and Miniſter for him, but as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>by their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> a before mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning perfection according to the Scriptures.</head>
               <p>THe onely true God, when he appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull, declared and ſaid, I am the Almighty God, and in his doctrine or by way of command ſaid unto <hi>Abraham, Walk before me and be thou perfect, Gen.</hi> 17.1. which doctrine <hi>Abraham</hi> received, and alſo Chriſt Jeſus our Lord in his doctrine, or by way of command he ſaid unto his Diſciples, and thoſe that he taught, who had grace and received the ſame, <hi>be ye perfect as your heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father is perfect, Mat.</hi> 5.48. And ſuch as preſſed after perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the doctrine of the Father and the Son, ſaid by the Spirit of truth, as many as are perfect be thus minded, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. to preſs others on to the ſame, and before the apoſtacy, whilſt the holy Ghoſt had the ordering in the true Church, and were of Counſell with the Miniſters of Chriſt, who preached the Goſpell with the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. they declared and ſaid, <hi>we preach wiſdome amongſt them that are perfect,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. and they taught in all wiſdome, labouring to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent every man perfect in Chriſt, <hi>Col</hi> 1.27, 28, 29. for which end they ſaid, Chriſt Jeſus when he aſcended upon high gave
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94811:9"/>gifts unto men, that is to ſay, for the perfecting of the Saints, <hi>&amp;c. Eph.</hi> 4.10, 11, 12, 13. who having grace according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the gift of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7. received the ſame, But ſince the apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, they deny the aforeſaid doctrine of perfection, and under a cover, they are not aſhamed to ſay and affirme, that the doctrine of ſinleſs perfection, was firſt bred by the Devil, ſecondly deteſted by Chriſt, thirdly and never received or truly beleeved in, by them that had any ſparke of true grace, when the ſaid Doctrine of perfection as aforementioned was firſt bred, or brought forth by the Almighty God, ſecondly and owned, approved of and preached by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thirdly and heartily received, beleeved in, preſſed after, attained unto, and preached by them that had received the Spirit of grace, and thereby were guided as aforeſaid; Then they that deny the ſaid doctrine of perfection aforementioned, and ſpeak ſo falſly of it as aforeſaid, doe make it appear that they are falſe Prophets and Miniſters of ſin, or Subjects to Anti-Chriſt, and no true Chriſtians, nor any true gifted men, but as Chriſt hath ſaid, by their fruits they are, or ſhall be known, therefore beware of them, and take heed of being devoured by the wolf, which long hath layen hid in a ſheeps cloathing, but now comes to be ſeen where the day is dawning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning laying on of hands, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe true Goſpel Miniſters before the apoſtacy declared and ſaid, that their ſufficiency was of God, who had made them able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the New Teſtament, not of the letter but of the Spirit; and they excluded ſelf, and denyed the inſufficiency and all the power of it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. But ſince the apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, they deny an inward call by the Lord God and his Spirit to be ſufficient to the work of the Miniſtry, without an outward call of men, not qualified thereunto by the holy Ghoſt, and ſo they ſet up a ſufficiency of ſelf, and prefers that before the power of the holy Ghoſt, and they that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94811:10"/>doe ſo muſt needs be falſe Prophets and Miniſters of ſin, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to Anti-Chriſt; and though under a pretence they would acknowledge the laying on of hands, yet they would not own the office, Counſell and authority of the holy Ghoſt in it, but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the holy Ghoſt, did either ſpeak in the Primitive time before the apoſtacy to them that laid hands on; or that they were qualified and impowered by the holy Ghoſt to the ſame, when in ſuch a caſe the Scripture is plaine, for the proof of the thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, who againſt the truth ſo affirme, for it is ſaid, and in holy Scripture left upon record, that there were in the Church that was at <hi>Antioch,</hi> certaine Prophets and Teachers, as namely <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> and <hi>Manaen</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> and as they miniſtred to the Lord and faſted, the holy Ghoſt ſaid ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the work whereunto I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, <hi>Acts.</hi> 13.1, 2. here it is plaine, that the holy Ghoſt ſpake to them, that miniſtred and faſted as aforeſaid, and the holy Ghoſt alſo declared, that he had called the ſaid <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> for the work of the Miniſtry, or as aforementioned, and moreover the holy Ghoſt ſaid by way of command, to them he ſpake unto, who laid on their hands, ſeparate me <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the work, whereunto I have called them, which was to the work of the Miniſtry, and if they had not in obedience to the holy Ghoſt direction and Counſell or order, ſeparated the ſaid <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> they had been oppoſite and diſobedient to the holy Ghoſts command and authority, but they were obedient and truly ſubject thereunto, and did what they were required by the holy Ghoſt, and when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they let them goe, but they attributed the work of ſending unto the holy Ghoſt, and not to the power of man without the holy Ghoſt, as the falſe Prophets doe now, ſo they being ſent forth by the holy Ghoſt departed unto <hi>Selucia,</hi> and from thence they ſayled to <hi>Cyprus, Acts.</hi> 13.3, 4. So it is clear that what they did in that thing, it was what they were qualified and impowered by the holy Ghoſt to doe, and they did it as a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of their ſubjection unto the holy Ghoſts order and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who was of Counſell with them, and did impower them to doe what he ſaw good and needfull to be done by them as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94811:10"/>unto him, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28, and he alſo for bad them doing what he would not have done by them, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. And ſo were of Counſell with them and a commander over them, as well as a guide unto them, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, teacher and comforter of them, according to the promiſe of Chriſt <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14.16, 17, &amp; 26. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13. and they owned him and his authority when he was come, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 1.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.20, 21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12. and they did not ſeek to exclude the office, direction, Counſell and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of him, that is to ſay of the holy Ghoſt, as the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt doe and a long time have done, who are now greatly offended at them, that own the holy Ghoſt to be of Counſell with them, and to teach, command, guide, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them according to the Scriptures; Therefore take notice, that they that ſeek to exclude the office and authority of the holy Ghoſt out of the Miniſtry and Churches, to the end that they may ſet up themſelves, they are the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Satan, or Subjects of Anti-Chriſt, who are the great enemies to the kingdome and Miniſtery of Chriſt, and are the Devils chief A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and for the upholding of him and his intereſt in people, therefore be warned and take heed of them, for they have had a long reign, <hi>and by their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> according to Chriſts ſaying, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15, 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now as God is pleaſed to bring people to the annointing and teaching of the Spirit of truth to teach them and qualify them with the holy Ghoſt, and thereby impower and ſend them to teach and require them to lay on hands, it is good, and ought to be done, for what the holy Ghoſt ſees good to be done, and requireth any to be ſubject to him in the thing, to act with and in the behalf of him, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be done, and they ought to yeeld their obedience as a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto him; but if men take upon them by their own wills and inventions or humane learning, to teach and lay on hands, and be not fitted, impowered, and qualified by the holy Ghoſt to the ſame, it is but ſelfiſh, and the work is their own, and not the Lords, and therefore it works little or no true Reformation, as experience of long, and ever ſince the apoſtacy, may or doth largely
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94811:11"/>evidence, and clearly demonſtrate againſt them. Oh that men would deny themſelves and ſelf-confidences, and all ſelf-refuges and intereſts thereof, as in reference to the work of the Miniſtry and worſhip of God, and alſo about the work of Reformation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and let the Lord alone with his work, and give up into his will, to be led, taught, counſelled and ordered by him, then would they ſee the emptineſs and inſufficiency of ſelf, and their own nothingneſs, as in reference to the work aforementioned; and ſo ſee the Lord to be the author and well-ſpring of all good and happineſs to mankinde, and alſo ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, teach, order, and eſtabliſh people and nations in the truth and true ſpirituall worſhip and Ordinances, both to the praiſe and glory of his grace, and the joy and comfort of their ſouls, and for the everlaſting good and happineſs of them: ſo would ſtocking, ſtoning, and perſecuting of men, and waſting their eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes, or ſpoyling their goods about Religion ceaſe, and the Lion and the Lamb would lye down together in peace for this rending tearing and devouring of men, and ſpoyling their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and eſtates, about matters of Religion and Reformation, hath been in the tranſgreſſion and alſo ſince the apoſtacy, and during the reign of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, and <hi>John</hi> ſaw were come, as before mentioned, which is many hundred years agoe or paſt, ſince they came.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning ſinging and the righteous man falling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the time of old, the true Prophets and people of God, when they were required to ſing praiſe to the Lord, either upon deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, or otherwiſe what the Lord required of them to ſing, they in obedience to him ſung, and were not without what to ſing, both in manner and matter, as was muſt acceptable and well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him; as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and through the red Sea, they ſung a ſong unto the Lord, and they declared that the Lord was both their ſong and their ſtrength, there ſalvation and their God, <hi>&amp;c. Exod.</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94811:11"/>15. and this was long before <hi>Davids</hi> conditions were put into thyme and meeter by <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold,</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> when they were to ſing, they had wherewithall to praiſe the Lord both in manner and matter, <hi>Judges</hi> 5. long before <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternholds</hi> time, ſo likewiſe <hi>David</hi> ſaid ſing unto the Lord, oh ye Saints of his, and give thanks at the remembrance of his holineſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.4. and this was long before <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold</hi> and ſome other Poets; put <hi>Davids</hi> conditions into rhyme and meeter for people to ſing; Therefore the Saints were furniſhed both in manner and matter with what to ſing, when it was required by the ſpirit of truth, of them and from them to doe the ſame, and alſo <hi>Solomon</hi> he had the ſong of ſongs, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.1. and knew what he was to ſing as it was required of him; and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was not without a ſong to ſing as it was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be done, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. Likewiſe the barren that had not borne, had matter of rejoycing, and knew what to ſing as it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. And if any want matter of praiſe and know not how to ſing, neither according to the right manner nor from the right matter, let them waite upon the Lord to teach them, that they may ſing to the praiſe of him, who is not awanting to them that patiently waite and put their truſt in him, and <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> after his complaint, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance ſaid ſing unto the Lord, praiſe ye the Lord, for he hath delivered the ſoul of the poor from the hand of evill doers, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.13. and moreover he ſpoke to the people by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the Lord to ſing with gladneſs for <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh praiſe and ſay, O Lord ſave thy people the remnant of <hi>Iſrael, Ier.</hi> 31.7 So when God requireth a people to ſing, he teacheth them what to ſay, without <hi>Hopkins,</hi> and <hi>Sternholds</hi> Poetry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who have put <hi>Davids</hi> prayers, prophecies, roaring and mournings into rhyme and meeter, with an addition alſo of their own inventions and lyes as appears; and as the Church in the time of old, and all the Saints and Servants of God had matter of praiſe given them, when they were required to ſing in obedience to the Lord and to his praiſe; ſo likewiſe in the true Churches of the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus before the apoſtacy, the bleſſed Apoſtle exhorted the Saints to be filled, with the Spirit, to the end that they might
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94811:12"/>ſing in Pſalms and Hymns and ſpirituall ſongs, ſinging and making melody in their heart to the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19. what was thoſe Pſalms, and Hymns and ſpirituall ſongs, that in their hearts they ſung to the Lord, ſeeing that <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold</hi> had not prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Davids</hi> conditions then in ryhme, and ſet them out therein according to the Art of Poetry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was not thoſe Hymns and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſongs ſuch as the redeemed then did and now may ſing? though none can or could learne them, but ſuch as were and are redeemed from among men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. And ſaid the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle before the apoſtacy, ſing with the Spirit and with the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. but ſince the apoſtacy the people it ſeems knew not what to ſing, till <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold,</hi> and ſome other Poets, made them ſongs of <hi>Davids</hi> conditions, and added thereunto their own inventions and lyes, and people are ſet to ſing them now by the falſe Prophets without the true ſpirit to guide them, and alſo without the true ſpirituall underſtanding; For when they ſing and ſay, <hi>O Lord I am not puft in minde,</hi> when they are puft in minde, doe they not lye in the name of the Lord, but if they were guided by the true ſpirit, they durſt not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them wilfully to lye, for Gods people doe not willingly lye; Therefore they that willingly lye they are not Gods people, but of their Faiher ſpoken of in <hi>Iohn</hi> 8 44. But as for the people and children of God, it is reported and declared by the ſpirit of truth thus; ſurely they are my people, children that will not lye, ſo he is their Saviour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.8. But they that ſing and ſay,<hi>they are not puft in min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> when they are full of minde, and ſay, <hi>they have no ſcornfull</hi> eye, when they are full of ſcorne, and looks with a ſcornfull eye one at another, and ſays, <hi>they are as a little child, that is weaned from his mothers breaſt,</hi> which is without actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion when they are nor ſo, and ſays all their bones ſhakes, (when they doe not ſo, and ſays, they goe mourning all the day long, when they doe not ſo, for ſuch as goe mourning all the day long, what time or part of that day have they to ſing, doe not ſuch both lye and ſing without the ſpirit, and true ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and is that any way to the praiſe of God, or is it not rather a ſelfiſh act, and when they follow <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Stern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told</hi> in their rhyme and additions in all things: doe they not ſing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94811:12"/>lies of the Scripture, and of the righteous man: when they ſay the Scripture plaine tells me, the righteous man offendeth ſeven times a day to thee, whereon thy wrath dependeth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when the Scripture doth not plaine tell any ſo; and that lye of <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternholds</hi> is grounded in people as a generall maxime, ſince the apoſtacy, as if none could be free from ſin, becauſe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man ſay they, ſins ſeven times a day, and they charge the Scripture with it, when the Scripture no where ſaith ſo, its true, there is a place in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> ſaith thus, lay not waite, O wicked man againſt the dwelling of the righteous, ſpoil not his reſting place, for a juſt man falleth ſeven times, and riſeth againe, but the wicked ſhall fall into miſchief, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.15, 16. but there is no mention of the righteous man falling ſeven times a day; and there is the place of Scripture, which makes moſt for that ſaying, when it doth not ſay ſo; but it ſeems <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold</hi> durſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to put in their own words, and ſay ſeven times a day to make meeter, and the people ignorantly have grounded a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon a lie, and ſo have lied of the righteous man and alſo of the Scripture, ſince the apoſtacy by reaſon of the falſe Prophets or Subjects of Anti-Chriſt; Neither doth that Scripture ſay in plaine tearms, that the juſt man ſins in thoſe ſeven times that he falls, but the wicked ſins becauſe he falls into miſchief, and lays waite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the dwelling of the righteous, and ſeeks to ſpoyl his reſting place as aforeſaid; moreover it is ſaid of the wicked, that they ſleep not unleſs they have done miſchief, and their ſleep is taken away, unleſs they cauſe ſome to fall, or ſuffer by them, for they cat the bread of wickedneſs, and drink the wine of violence, but the righteous is counſelled to avoid the way of evill men, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16, 17. and are forbidden to enter into the path of the wicked, and if the righteous man ſhould ſin ſeven times a day, he would both enter into the path of the wicked, and walk in the way of evill men: But it is ſaid, that the path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.18. but the way of the wicked is as darkneſs, ver. <hi>19.</hi> Therefore it is to be obſerved, that there is as much difference between the way of the righteous, and the way of the wicked, as between light and darkneſs, and that they, that deny the light
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94811:13"/>are ignorant of the way of the righteous, and moſt acquainted with darkneſs the way of the wicked; and I ſay there is a vaſte dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between ſinning ſeven times in the whole, and ſinning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſeven times a day, if it was ſo, that the juſt man did ſin ſeven times in thoſe ſeven falls; yet the juſt man he may fall ſeverall times, and not ſin in thoſe falls, for it is ſaid of <hi>Job,</hi> that he was a perfect and an upright man as any was upon the face of the earth at that time, <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. and he held his integrity as the Lord ſaid, though Satan moved the Lord againſt him, to have deſtroyed him without cauſe, <hi>Iob</hi> 2.3. and he fell into many troubles or tryalls, ſufferings and exerciſes, as juſt men oftentimes doe, yet it is ſaid, <hi>that in all this</hi> Job <hi>did not ſin with his lips, Iob</hi> 2. 10. And <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, if any man offend not in word, the ſame is a perfect man, and able alſo to bridle the whole body; And the juſt or righteous man may fall into troubles, tryals, and exerciſes, for the tryall of their faith and patience, and yet in thoſe falls may be kept from ſin, for many are the troubles of the righteous, but the Lord delivereth them out of them all; the Lord upholdeth them that ſo fall, and raiſeth up all thoſe that be bowed down, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.14. for the Lord upholdeth them with his hand, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Prayer.</head>
               <p>IN the true Church before the apoſtacy; the true Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſaid; I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the underſtanding alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14,15. But ſince the apoſtacy the falſe Prophets or Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt and Subjects of ſin, they pray without the true Spirit guiding therein and without the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; for though they ſay, <hi>Our father which art in Heaven,</hi> they are ready to account it blaſphemy, for any to ſay I am a child or Son of God; and they alſo ſay in one of the Petitions in the Lords Prayer, <hi>viz forgive us our treſpaſſes as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us;</hi> here they pray to God to forgive them their treſpaſſes committed againſt him, as they forgive them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94811:13"/>againſt them, when they doe not forgive ſuch, as they account to be treſpaſſers againſt them, but rather ſeeks to deſtroy them by impriſonment, and ſending to the houſe of correction, and by abuſing them with cruell perſecution; Doe ſuch pray for any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of God, who doe not forgive, when they pray for their forgiveneſs, as they forgive others; and if any be moved of the Lord, to goe and ſpeak to a Prieſt, or a company of people led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray by a ſpirit of errour, to the end that they may returne and ſeek the Lord, doe not the Prieſts account it a treſpaſs againſt them, and inſtead of paſſing it by with a forgiveneſs, if it be by them accounted a treſpaſs, doe they not ſeek rather to puniſh to the uttermoſt, if ſo, doe they not pray without underſtanding, when they pray to be forgiven as they forgive others? when they never intend to doe as they ſay, and doe they not alſo pray that God may be avenged on them, as they ſeek to be avenged on the people of God, that comes to ſpeak unto them in pure obedience to the Lord, which the Pariſh Prieſts accounts a treſpaſs againſt them; But if they were in the truth, they need not to be afraid to be ſpoken unto by a ſervant of the Lord; is it not deceit that needs to be guarded with a law; to the end that none may ſpeak, unto them in obedience to the Lord; likewiſe in the true Church before the apoſtacy it was an order amongſt them, that if any thing were revealed to them that ſat by, they might ſpeak, and the firſt hold his peace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30. But ſince the apoſtacy, the caſe is altered in the Pariſh. Churches ſo called, and none muſt ſpeak their that ſits by, if the Lord command it, under paine of impriſonment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is not that in errour to the true Churches order; conſider well of it and read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14, 30, 31, 32, 33. And before the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy to pray by the true Spirit was much commended, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt true beleevers in the true Church, it was much practiſed, and prayer could not well be made acceptable to God but by the Spirit, or they knew not how to pray as they ought, without the direction and aſſiſtance of the holy Spirit, which made and now maketh interceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God; But ſince the apoſtacy, prayer by the Spirit hath been much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, and the falſe Prophets and Subjects of Anti-Chriſt, are ready to mock and jeer at them, that preach and pray by and with the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94811:14"/>Spirit, according to the Scriptures, as the Saints formerly did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. <hi>&amp;c. Eph.</hi> 6.18, 19. But who are they that jeer at this now, except the falſe Prophets and Subjects to Anti-Chriſt, who like hypocrites pray ſtanding in the Synagogues, contrary to the true Chriſts command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5. that they may be ſeen and praiſed of men of like minds, but as Chriſt hath ſaid they have their reward, <hi>and by their fruits they ſhall be known,</hi> but Chriſt bids his to beware of ſuch, and ſaith, that though for a precence they make long prayers, who devour wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes, and have the chief ſeats in the Synagogues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet not withſtanding theſe, faith Chriſt, ſhall receive greater dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as may be read, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.38, 39, 40.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning free-grace.</head>
               <p>Grace is the gift of God, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.34. and what is more free than gift, yet ſome ſay, curſed be all they that ſay, grace is free, and let all the people ſay Amen; I ſay let ſuch be marked, for they are the enemies of Chriſt, and are falſe Prophets, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent or great for the intereſt of Anti-Chriſt, for the Lord God is a Sun and a ſhield, the Lord will give grace and glory, no good thing will he with hold from them that walk uprightly, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 84 11. And grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. and the true Chriſtians beleeved through grace, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.27. and it the grace had not been free, through which they beleeved, might they not have died in their ſins and periſhed; becauſe they could not chime it as a debt, and they could not morit it, becauſe whilſt und bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evers, what had they of an equall worth to give for it, they could not purchaſe it by any act or thing of theirs; Therefore is was and is a gift, and being a gift it is free, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17, 18. And before the apoſtacy the true Goſpe-Miniſter hath declared the grace of God, which bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſs and worldlineſs we ſhould live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent evill world, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11.12. But ſince the apoſtacy, the falſe Prophets and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94811:14"/>Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt; They deny the freeneſs, and ſufficiency of the grace of God, and ſo denyes the doctrine of the Spirit of grace, to the end that they may ſet up ſelf and live in ſinfulneſs, drunkenneſs and abundance of ungodilineſs, in deſpite to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace, but great will be the puniſhment of ſuch as doe deſpite to the ſpirit of grace, and turne into wantonneſs, as you may read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28,19. <hi>Iude</hi> 4. ſuch are of the number of the falſe Prophets and Subjects to Anti-Chriſt; Therefore beware of them, for by their fruits they are known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Faith.</head>
               <p>The true Miniſters of the Goſpel before the apoſtacy, they came not with the enticing words of mans wiſdome, but in demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit and of power, to the end that the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians faith might not ſtand in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.5. and the true Goſpel-Miniſter, ſaid to the true Chriſtians <hi>by grace are ye ſaved through faith;</hi> and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God not of works, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8, 9. But ſince the apoſtacy the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt, that deny the grace to be free, and ſay it is not ſufficient, they deny the ſufficiency of it, and ſo denies ſaluation by grace through faith, and ſets up their own works or ſelf actings, to the end that they may act Anti-Chriſts part, and boaſt of their own doings by the power of ſelf, who deny the power of God, in which the Saints faith doth ſtand; and turns curſers of them, that own the true faith; who ſay, curſed are all they, that ſay, faith is without ſin; as many falſe Prophets in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have done, true faith is the gift of God, and a fruit of the Spirit of God, as the bleſſed Apoſtle hath ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8.9. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. and God gives faith, but be gives not ſin; Therefore the faith which Cod gives, muſt needs be a faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, and what ſoever is not of faith is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſin, is not of faith, nor any part or degree of the ſame; true faith purifieth the heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. but ſin polluteth, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.21, 22, 23. true faith is pretious, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. but ſo is not ſin;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94811:15"/>true faith in Chriſt is the Saints victory over the world, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 4. therefore it is a faith without ſin, and Chriſt is the author of the true faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. but he is not the author of ſin; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that faith which he is the author of, muſt needs be a faith without ſin; Then they that ſay faith is not without ſin, they muſt needs be falſe Prophets and Miniſters of ſin, or ſubjects of Anti-Chriſt, who doe no leſs than ſay, the gift of God is not without ſin, and that Chriſt is the author of ſin; Oh horrid blaſphemy and wicked deluſion, for if faith be not without ſin, as they ſay it is not, then God in giving faith, muſt give ſin accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the falſe Prophets account, which he doth not; and if faith be not without ſin, as the falſe Prophets ſay it is not; then Chriſt in being the author of faith, might be the author of ſin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the falſe Prophets account; therefore people, now that you have ſuch a cleer diſcovery of them, and in regard that their fruits doe ſo plainly deſcribe them, if you yet follow them, and be ſtill ſeduced by them, it is becauſe you are in love with them, and are willing to be led aſtray by them; and if the blinds lead the blinde, ſhall not both fall into the ditch, as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. now you are warned and I am cleared; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſeparate and come out from among them, and touch not the uncleane thing, all you that regard the glory of God and you ſouls good, that you may [be hid in the day of the Lords wrath, and] be received into favour with him, and numbred amongſt his Sons and Daughters, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>By a ſervant of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and a true lover of all that love the truth, as it is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſus; and Wiſheth, grace, mercy and peace to all the Saints in Chriſt Ieſus, and much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and bleſſing to all the true Goſpel-Miniſters, who are faithfull to the work of the Miniſtry of the true Chriſt, that ſaid the falſe Prophets ſhould come, <hi>Mat. 7. &amp; 24. Chap.</hi> and gave counſell to his to beware of them; and I being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the work of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel of Chriſt, am ingaged much in love to him, and as a partaker with the reſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94811:15"/>of the true Goſpel Miniſters, I am bound in love to write this testimony againſt the falſe Prophets, and for the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all honeſt people, to the end that they may be aware of them, and ſo remain yours, as you are the Lords faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Meſſengers and friends.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Written at</hi> Bridlenton <hi>Key in the beginning of</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>the twelfth month in the year,</hi> 1657 <hi>c</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>R. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="queries">
               <head>A few Queries to the Pariſh-Prieſts, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>VVAS not the tenths of every Pariſh, ſince the apoſtacy firſt granted to their Incumbents by the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>Whether was not the Engliſh Church in the time of apoſtacy ſince the coming of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets long after the Birth of Chriſt, founded in the eſtate of Popery and Prelacy, and did not the Kings and Nobles of the land, and their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors at that time, to the end that they and the people might be informed, and for other works where the Churches were founded, and for the ſouls of the Founders their Heirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> give certain poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, as well in Fees, Lands, Rents, as in advouſons, which did extend to a great value, and were they not aſſigned by the ſaid Founders to the Prelates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſuſtaine the ſame charge, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the poſſeſſions, which were aſſigned to Arch-Biſhops,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94811:16"/>Biſhops, Abbots. Priors. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> Earls, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and other great men of the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And did they not think to merit by their works in ſo doing, and had not the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> then a great hand amongſt them, when the Church was ſo founded, and the poſſeſſions by the founders to the Prelates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were ſo aſſigned yea or nay?See the Statute of the 25. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. in the year, 1350.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> III.</head>
                  <p>Was not, Tithes free for any man to give after the Apoſtles times, till the time of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, and did not he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree by his decretall Epiſtle, at his Councel held at <hi>Lateran,</hi> that Tithes ſhould be paid to the Parſons and Rectors of Pariſhes, and did they not ſo become <hi>lexterrae,</hi> and into parrochiall rights ſo called there from. See <hi>Cooks</hi> 2. part Inſtit. fol, 641, 642. was not here the riſe of Tithes in the time of apoſtacy, to the Pariſh-Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And was they not eſtabliſhed by an earthly Law, and ſo not <hi>jure divino,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> IV.</head>
                  <p>Had not the Pope a covetous end to himſelf, in cauſing Tithes to be paid as aforeſaid, and was not his end, to have the tenth part of the tenths in imitation of the Jewiſh high Prieſts, or as may be ſeen in <hi>Cooks</hi> 2. part. Inſtitut. And whether is the Popes part as yet caſt out, from amongſt the Pariſh-Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> V.</head>
                  <p>Had not the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> the order and rule amongſt Tithes and the Prieſthood, and gifter of the Arch Biſhopricks, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks when they fell void here in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. until the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight; See <hi>Cooks</hi> 2. part. Inſtit. fol. 652, 653. and Stat. the 24. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12. and Stat. 28. of <hi>Hent</hi> the 8.10.16. Stat. 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.20, 11. — And was not the Arch-Biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94811:16"/>
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. before they were elected, conſecrated and inveſted into their offices and dignities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> firſt to be nominated and preſented by the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and did they not from him, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pope, or by his order and appointment, till then receive Bulls, Pales, Briefs, Reſcripts, Delegacies, Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Benedictions and Ceremonies, and all things as it is ſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite thereunto belonging, yea or nay? See the Stat, of the 25. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8, Chap. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> VI.</head>
                  <p>And after the Pope was denied to be ſupreame head on earth of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was not <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, as Kings and Queens of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> declared to be head on earth of the Church of <hi>England</hi> aforeſaid, and was not the Prieſthood, after the Pope was denyed to be head, to hold their places and Benefices, which they received before in the Popes reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Orders, Reſcripts, Delegacies, Bulls, Pales, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they had been tollerated and ſet therein by the Pope and his Bulls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea or nay; See the Stat. of the 24. of <hi>Hen</hi> 8,12. and 25. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.20, 21. Chap.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> VII.</head>
                  <p>And when the Pope was caſt out and denyed to be head of the Church, and <hi>Henry</hi> the eight ſet up to be head, did they not enact and declare how to ordaine, and conſecrate Arch-Biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in <hi>England</hi> after that, and was not the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> ſet up partly like a little Pope, and were not they of the order of the Prieſthood to receive under his ſeal authentick to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> Orders, Grants, Reſcripts, Build, Pales, Briefs, Faculties, Diſpenfations, Benedictions and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and ſuch things as uſed to be had arid obtained of the Pope at the See of <hi>Rome</hi> before that time, if ſo wherein did the Prieſthood of <hi>England</hi> ſucceed the Apoſtlés of Chriſt, but rather the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and whether did they differ much at that time from the Popiſh Prieſts yea or nay?. See the Statutes afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94811:17"/>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> VIII.</head>
                  <p>Was not the Maſs book in force, till the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and did not he deny the Maſs book, to ſet up the Common Prayer book in its ſtead, 1. &amp; 2. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Chap. 1. and was not that cryed up as the true Chriſtian Proteſtant Religion, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the publick profeſſion of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and was not that mightily cryed up whilſt an outward Law gave it life, and did not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> deny the Common Prayer book to ſet up, the Maſs book in <hi>England</hi> againe, and was not that cryed up for its time, and while an outward Law gave life to it, was it not both by prieſts and people had in great eſteeme, and they by Law bound to the ſame yea or nay? <hi>Seſſio ſecunda Anno Mariae primo</hi> Chap. 2.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> IX.</head>
                  <p>Did not Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> deny the Maſs book, and ſet up the Common Prayer book againe, and by a Law binde people to the ſame, thereby denying all Laws that was for the upholding any other worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> Chap. 2. and did not that ſtand in force till of lace that it was made void by act of Parliament, and if all that Religion and worſhip was falſe and not true, hath not the prieſts been the greater deceivers, and manifeſted themſelves to be the falſe Prophets, and have they not ſhewed themſelves and their riſe to be from the Pope, and are they not on the top of Popery and ground of ſuperſtition yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> X.</head>
                  <p>Had not the Pope his penſions and <hi>Peter</hi> pence, and other things in <hi>England</hi> till <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and when <hi>Henry</hi> the eight put the Pope out of them, did he not let the Biſhops and prieſts into the worlds honours, or endow them with the Popes ornaments, as penſions, Eaſter reckonings, ſmoke pence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Tithes, Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to keep them from corruption and ſiniſter
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94811:17"/>affection, and if corruption and ſiniſter affection be ſin, and prieſts plead for the ſame terme of life, doe not they that ſo pleade, both plead againſt the Law, and one end for which Tithes were given, and ſo plead againſt Tithes terme of life, and impleading againſt the intent of the Law, and one of the chief ends for which Tithes were given, doe they not plead thereby, that they have no right to them, and ſo make them void by that plea, yea or nay? alſo ſee the Statute of the 24. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 12.25. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.21. &amp; 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.20.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XI.</head>
                  <p>And when Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> had ſet up the Common prayer book, and that uniforme worſhip which is now denyed; was not the pariſh-prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be made or called to the Miniſtry by the act of Parliament made the thirteenth of <hi>Eliz.</hi> Chap. 12. yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XII.</head>
                  <p>Was not the pariſh-prieſts, Miniſters or preachers by vertue of the ſaid Statute of the thirteenth of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. who held or hold their places and Benefices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by vertue thereof to ſubſcribe to the Articles agreed of in the Convocation holden at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1562. And did they not receive Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the ſeal authentick of the Arch-Biſhop? And were they not to read the ſame aſſent and ſubſcription to the ſaid Articles, with a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their unfeigned aſſent, thereunto, in the pariſh Church ſo called, where they were to ſerve as a prieſt, Farſon, Miniſter, Curate or Clerke, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the time of Common prayer or open ſervice, at or ſoon after their Induction, being the age of 23. years, or upon refuſall of the ſame aforementioned were they not to be <hi>ipſo facto, viz.</hi> deprived of their ſpirituall promotions, as if they were then naturally dead, and their diſpenſations to be void, yea or nay?</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94811:18"/>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XIII.</head>
                  <p>And was not that the Back door, or outward way of calling by which the Pariſh Prieſts, Parſons, Miniſters, Curates, or Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> entered into the parochiall miniſtration, and not by Chriſt the true door, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. and right way by which his Miniſters doe enter into the true Goſpel-diſpenſation and adminiſtration, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, and is not the ſaid back-door ſhut againſt the pariſh Miniſters, or that way of calling made void in Law; for is it not enacted and declared by the Stat. of the 13. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. <hi>viz.</hi> that all Inſtitutions, Inductions, Admiſſions, Licences and Tolerations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about the office of the Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereunto, <hi>viz.</hi> the Statute aforeſaid ſhall be meerly void in Law, as if they never were, and is that Law repealed that ſaith ſo; was there none accounted true Miniſters all that time, if ſo, but what were called according to it, if not, was not the Miniſtry a falſe Miniſtry all that time, ſeeing that way and order of calling is denyed, and was not many or moſt of the pariſh-prieſts and publick Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſerves now who were called in the time of the late B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhops, called by it; and olerated according to the ſaid Statute, and if that was a falſe Miniſtry, and a falſe way of calling to the work of the Miniſtry, and more Popiſh than poſtolicall, when was there any true Goſpel-Miniſters in <hi>Englan</hi> ſince the apoſtacy, and coming of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets amongſt them of the parochiall order and that miniſtration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath there been none truly ordained and called, till of late within theſe few years, ſince they left the old way of calling by a teſtimony, under the ſeal authentick of the Arch-Biſhop and as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, or was not that way as much cried up for the right way in its time, whilſt the Law favoured it, as any other way was, or is the way and calling of Miniſters to the Goſpel-Miniſtry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures ſo alterable as to change, as the outward government changeth, yea or nay?</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94811:18"/>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XIV.</head>
                  <p>Is it not declared and enacted, or at leaſt was it not ſo, by the Statute of the 13. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. that none ſhall or ſhould be made Miniſter or admitted to preach, till he was 23. years of age, nor adminiſter the Sacraments, ſo called, untill he was 24. years of age, nor unleſs he bring or brought to the Biſhop of that Dioceſs from men known to the Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a teſtimoniall both of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and of his profeſſing the doctrine expreſſed in the ſaid Articles agreed of in the Convocation holden at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1562. And moreover that none ſhould be admitted to the order of a Deacon or Miniſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs he did or ſhould firſt ſubſcribe to the ſaid Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and was not every pariſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to read his aſſent and ſubſcription to the ſaid Articles with a Declaration of his unfeigned aſſent thereunto, in the pariſh Church ſo called, where he was to ſerve; and was he not bound to read it in the time of Common Prayer or open ſervice, at or ſoon after his Induction, or elſe upon refuſall to be, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> as aforeſaid, and his diſpenſation made void, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if that were judged by the Prieſts, Clergy-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be the onely right way of ordaining Miniſters and legall calling of them, according to the Inſtitution of the Apoſtolicall order, recorded in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to be the ſtanding rule, or onely way of ordination for ever after to the work of the Miniſtry and none elſe, and if the Prieſts Preachers or pariſh Miniſters, did ſubſcribe to the Articles agreed of, and upon ſuch an account declared their unfeigned aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto, and did read their Declaration of that aſſent and ſubſcription thereunto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> openly in the time of Common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and as aforeſaid; How ſoon are they changed and overturned in that; and have they not ſhewed that their aſſent and ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was feigned, and ſo hypocriticall and not reall. And if that were the right way of ordaining Miniſters, and the onely legall way of calling them, according to the Scriptures and Chriſts In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> why was it forſaken and made void for any ſelf-end, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if that were not the onely right way of Ordination and calling of Miniſters to the work of the Miniſtry; then whether
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94811:19"/>were not all they that were ſo ordained and called, falſly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly called, and not according to the Scriptures, if ſo, were they not the greater deceivers, and doe they not make it appear, that there hath been no true Goſpel-Miniſters in the parochial mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, nor no right way of ordaining and calling to the work of that Miniſtry till of late, according to their account, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing the pariſh-miniſters have left that, their old way of ordination and calling, &amp; have they not been conſtrained to beg to the Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or at leaſt have they not been beholden to them, or to ſome in outward authority appointed for the Nationall Government, to finde them out a way of ordaining, calling, or approving of Miniſters, and if they had not found them out one, or done ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them about the ſame, had not the pariſh-miniſters been clearly rooted, and run off from their foundation, about calling, ordination, and toleration, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XV.</head>
                  <p>And if none might have been admitted to miniſter, in the behalf of the Lord, till they had been 23. years of age, but by a Nationall Law have been bound from the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the miniſtry, untill ſuch a time, or elſe have ſuffered by the Law for ſo doing; might not <hi>Samuel</hi> a true Prophet the ſervant of the Lord, by ſuch a Law have been bound from being a Miniſter in the legall diſpenſation, when he was a little child, and bound about with a linnen Ephod, and ſo not have been admitted to miniſter to the Lord, or in his behalf in that miniſtration, becauſe a child, or not 23. years of age, might he not either by ſuch a Law have been bound from the work of the miniſtry, though the Lord had called him to it, and by his word both eſtabliſhed and fitted him for it according to the Scripture, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.18.19.1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.19, 20, 21. or elſe by that Law have ſuffered, and been by men condemned or not approved, becauſe not called to the miniſtry according to their Law, if ſo, was not ſuch a Law, <hi>viz.</hi> 13. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. as the pariſh-prieſts, preachers and Miniſters were called, ordained, and tolerated by, or according unto their miniſtry, a Law directly contrary to the Scriptures, and in oppoſition to God and his word, or way of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the miniſtry as aforeſaid, yea or nay?</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94811:19"/>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XVI.</head>
                  <p>And might not Chriſt Jeſus himſelf, by ſuch a Law have been bound and not admitted, to have done his Fathers will at twelve years of age, when at ſuch an age he waxed ſtrong in ſpirit, being filled with wiſdome, and the grace of God was upon him, ſo that he was fit to diſpute, and did at twelve years of age doe his Fathers buſineſs, as may be read, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.40, 41, 42. to the 50. But if it had been of late years, when the Common prayer book, and that way of calling to the work of the Miniſtry, according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the 13. of. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. were in force, if not yet, might not Chriſt himſelf, if he had then been perſonally preſent in <hi>England,</hi> have by that Law been diſallowed of, and not admitted to the work of the Lord at twelve years of age, nor afterward, no more then by the Jews and chief prieſts he was, who queſtioned his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and ſaid, have any of the rulers or Phariſees beleeved on him; if ſo, was not that Law directly oppoſite to the Scriptures, and contrary to the way of God as aforeſaid, and if he had pleaded his inward ſpirituall call, and ſaid his Father had ſent him, would not the rulers and chief prieſts in <hi>England</hi> have oppoſed and ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n inward call without an outward, according to the Law of man before mentioned, would not have been ſufficient, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> VII.</head>
                  <p>And if none might have been admitted to Miniſter in the behalf of the Lord, but ſuch as ſubſcribed to the Articles agreed of in the Convocation holden at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1562. and alſo ſuch as did aſſent to the ſame, and read their ſubſcription to the ſaid Articles, with a Declaration of their unfeigned aſſent thereunto in the pariſh Church, where they were to ſerve in the time of Common prayer, at or ſoon after their Induction, being 23. years of age, and before their admiſſion brought the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs from men known to him, a teſtimoniall of their profeſſing the doctrine expreſſed in the ſaid Articles, that they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a teſtimoniall under his Seal authentick, and be tolerated, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:94811:20"/>according to the 13. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. which was the Pariſh-Prieſts way of ordination and toleration, it ſeems till of late that there, was no Biſhops to give them orders, or a teſtimoniall under their ſeal authentick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might not by the ſame rule or Law, all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, as true Prophets and Apoſtles, that was ſent by the Lord God and his Spirit according to the Scriptures, have been diſallowed of, and neither admitted nor tolerated, becauſe they had not the Common prayer book; nor the Articles that was but agreed of, in the Convocation holden at <hi>London,</hi> as they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed of in the time of apoſtacy, therefore they could not ſubſcribe to them, nor read any Declaration of their unfeigned aſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in the Pariſh Church, becauſe they had no ſuch Pariſh Church, nor Popiſh ſtuffe among the true Goſpel-Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the apoſtacy ſpoken of in the Scriptures; and if the Lord ſhould have ſent any by his Spirit, according to the order of the true Prophets and Apoſtles, might they not have been diſallowed of, and not admitted into the work of the Miniſtry in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> if they could not ſubmit to that Popiſh ſtuffe and inventions of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, or errour of the pariſh, prieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that came in ſince the apoſtacy, and muſt not ſuch as the Lord, ſends now and hereafter, by his Spirit, and according to his word, be diſallowed and denyed by the pariſh-prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if they can not ſubmit to their other inventions or former Popiſh traditions, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Was it not declared in the Statute of the 13. of <hi>Eliz:</hi> 12. that none ſhould be admitted to adminiſter the Sacraments, when the Common prayer book and that Service was in force, untill he were 24. years of age, and was not the Sacraments and Sacramentalls formerly, whilſt the Maſs book was in force, commonly called the Maſs, ſee the Statute of the 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. Chap. 1. And if the Sacraments and Sacramentals were called the Maſs, whilſt the Maſs-book was in force, was they not the ſame in the time of the Common prayer book, and are they not the ſame that they were, ſeeing the Scripture ſpeaks nothing of either Sacraments or Maſs, yea or nay?</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:94811:20"/>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XIX.</head>
                  <p>Did not the Pope after the apoſtacy, when he cauſed Tithes, Oblations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be paid to the Pariſh-Prieſts, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cauſe the ſame to be paid to them, and ſuch like onely as were of the Popiſh order, and preached up his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and obſerved the Maſs book, and that ſervice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip onely, which was then ſet up and by him allowed of, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XX.</head>
                  <p>If ſo then, whether ought not thoſe Tithes, Oblations, Obven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to have ceaſed and returned back to the people againe, when he, and that worſhip, and ſervice was denyed, for which they were payed, or is the worſhip and ſervice in the ground of Superſtition and Popery made void, where and by whom Tithes Oblations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are received, which the Pope at firſt ſince the apoſtacy, created or cauſed to be paid, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXI:</p>
                  <p>Did King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. when he denyed the Pope to be head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> called the holy Church then, deny the Tithes and make them void, which the Pope had created or cauſed before to be paid, and did he put down Tithes to cauſe them to returne to the people againe, whoſe right they were, before the Pope cauſed the people to pay to them to his Prieſts, Parſons, and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or did not King <hi>Henry</hi> and his Parliament, when the Pope was denyed to be head of the Church, confer and ſtate the Popes former Creation or gift, as Tithes, Oblations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the Prelates, or the Kings Pariſh-Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and were they not then to obſerve to preach up the Kings intereſt for the ſame, or bound to performe and obſerve that Religion, Worſhip or Service, which was <hi>ſet</hi> up and allowed of by him and his ſucceſſors, to wit, Kings and Queens, and had not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94811:21"/>the ſaid King and his ſucceſſors, as Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> the Popes part conferred or ſtated on them, <hi>viz.</hi> the tenth part of the tenths, and as the Pope before had whilſt he was head of the Church, and was not the pariſh-prieſts, Parſons, and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> content to be the Kings prieſts, for the Popes Livery or reward, as Tithes, Oblations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and were they not taken by the King from the Pope, his Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and after conferred on them, to wit the Kings, Prelates, pariſh-priefts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hath not both the King and his Prelates, and both Popery and Prelacy been much denyed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought not Tithes which came from the Pope, to the King and his Prelates, pariſh-prieſts, Parſons and Rectors to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed and made void, and to have returned to the people againe, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXII.</head>
                  <p>Or how can the people truly ſay, that they are redeemed from that ſuperſtition, which came in by the Pope and Popiſh traine, as in reference to the Miniſtry, was Tithes that the Pope cauſed to be paid, ever made void in the ground, but rather conferred upon the pariſh-prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and have thoſe Tithes, Oblations, Obventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the Pope firſt created or cauſed to be paid, which afterward was removed from the popiſh Prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conferred it ſeems upon the Kings, Prelates, and upon the pariſh-prieſts Parſons, and Rectors, Curates and Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſo, I ſay were they ever ſince there was no King in <hi>England,</hi> yet made void to returne to the people againe, who deny both the Pope and that popiſh traine, or have not the pariſh-Miniſters, and publick preachers in that miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begged the Tithes, and have they not laboured to get them conferred and ſtated on them, ſince there was no King in <hi>England,</hi> nor Prieſt, or pariſh-miniſters of his, leaſt Tithes ſhould from them have been void, and have returned to the people again or to ſome other charitable uſe, and ſo into their right place, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from their place by the Pope to the popiſh prieſts, and after that removed from them it ſeems, unto the Kings prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94811:21"/>and ſince then if Tithes had been thrown down, and the Popes gift or creation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made void, that the Prieſts or pariſh-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters might have been left to the Seal of their miniſtry, or have had ſome new gift given freely by the people onely, that ownes them for their miniſters in their mimiſtry, would it not have been more agreeable to the Scripture, and might they not the better, in truth and honeſty have cryed down Popery, and been the more enabled to convince the gain-ſayer, but as yet, are they not on the popiſh ground, and is not that foundation, and rubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh unremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, from amongſt the pariſh-miniſters or publick Preachers, that gape for and yet receive Tithes, which the Pope firſt cauſed to be paid, and was never yet taken away or clearly removed, to returne to the people againe, and were they not their proper right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance after the coming of Chriſt, to put an end to the old Covenant and prieſt-hood, and to eſtabliſh another upon better promiſes, and without payment of Tithes before the Popes time, and when that is denyed and removed, in ground, root and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which come in by the Pope and his traine, in the time of Apoſtacy, will not Tithes then be the peoples proper right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance againe, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXIII.</head>
                  <p>All you Pariſh-prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, publick preachers or Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who ſay you have Tithes, wages or hire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet preſumes to ſay you bleſs God, you preach not for Tithes, Wages, Augmentations, Stipends or hire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I aske the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether you receive the ſaid Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon conſideration or no conſideration, if upon no conſideration? why may not any other man receive them as well as you: And if you receive Tithes, Augmentations, Stipends, or hire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon conſideration, Is not preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The conſideration upon which you receive them? If ſo, what difference is there between preaching for Tithes, Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, Augmentations, Wages or hire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And receiving them upon the ſaid conſideration of preaching? do you think ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſufficient to hide you under from underſtanding men, or to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie you in the fight of God, as to ſay, you have Tithes, Stipends,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94811:22"/>augmentations, Wages or hire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But you bleſs God, you ſay you preach not for them: And if you receive them upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of preachig as aforeſaid, whether do you not plainly make it appear that you both preach for them, and take upon you to lie in the name of the Lord, in your former ſaying about them, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXIV.</head>
                  <p>And all you pariſh-prieſts, Parſons and Rectors, Curates and Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That was called, ordained and inſtituted in the time of the late Biſhops, when you uſed the Common prayer and ſign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Did you not conclude that little children were conceived in ſin, and borne in iniquity, and alſo ſaid except they were regenerate and borne againe they could not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; and as the onely way and means of Regeneration, and to fit them for the kingdome of God, as you pretended, &amp;c. Did you not ſay a little Common prayer over the Infant, and alſo ſprinkle a little water out of a Fount on the Childs face; and ſign it with the ſign of the Croſs, and the like Popiſh ſtuffe; and then conclude and make people believe, that ſuch a Child was Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and made an inheritour of the kingdome of God, &amp;c. And did you not account that to be the onely way to the new-Birth, after you had read a little Common prayer over the Infant, and ſigned it with the ſign of the Croſs as aforeſaid, then ſaying, <hi>Dearly beloved, ſeeing this Child is Regenerate or borne againe, let us give thanks,</hi> as if the Common prayer and the ſign of the Croſs were the onely way to the new-birth, and none elſe, and if ſo, that is now made void by act of Parliament? Then what way have you deviſed and imagined ſince then about the ſame, or is your deviſed and imagined way about it of any more force, or in any wiſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to ſalvation any more than your fore-fathers devices, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pope and Arch-Biſhops were. And if the former was falſe and not true; then was not all they who were Baptized with the Common prayer, and the ſign of the Croſs by the pariſh-prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> falſly Baptized; and was not all that Baptiſm falſe, if ſo, then when was there any Regenerate and born againe, in and by that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94811:22"/>popiſh ſtuffe, and moreover when was there any truly Baptized in <hi>England</hi> by the Kings, Prelates, or pariſh-prieſts, Parſons, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Curates and Clerks; and was not that way, and Baptiſm afore mentioned cryed up as the onely way and Baptiſm, whilſt the nationall Law favoured it, or tolerated the pariſh-prieſts, Parſons, Rectors, Curates and Clerks in and about the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the aforeſaid pretended way to the new-birth and Infants-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: And if you ſay it was true and not falſe? why have you leſt it, or doth the Ordinances and miniſtry of Chriſt according to the Scriptures, alter and change at every change of a nationall Government, if not, then whether are you the Miniſters of Chriſts, according to the ſpirit of truth, and agreeable to the Scriptures, or nationall Miniſters onely, like unto your fore-fathers, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXV.</head>
                  <p>And have you not engaged people by promiſe and vow to be perfect and free from ſin, upon which account were they not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be Chriſtians and Member of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when you pretended to enter them into the Covenant of Baptiſm, and make them children of God, and inheritour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by cauſing Suerties, as Peoffies in truſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Childs Infancy; to promiſe and vow in the behalf of the Child, <hi>That it ſhould for ſake the Devil and all his works, the pompes and vanities of the wicked world, and all the ſinfull luſts of the fleſh, and carnall deſires of the ſame,</hi> and that they ſhould neither follow them, nor be led by them: <hi>but that they ſhould keep Gods holy will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements all the days of their life;</hi> and was not the Children by their own confeſſion and promiſe bound to the ſame, when they were formerly Catechiſed after they came as, it was ſaid, to years of diſcretion; and to forſake the Devil and all his works, is not that to forſake the worker of iniquity, aſwell as to forſake all ſin and unrighteouſneſs whatſoever, becauſe all ſin is the works of the Devill, who is the chief worker of iniquity, and for people to keep Gods holy will and Comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dements all the days of their life. Is not that to refuſe to ſerve the Devill all the days of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94811:23"/>their life, and not to commit ſin or obey his commands any of the dayes of their life? How comes it to paſs then, that now you labour to abſolve peop1e from their former engagement, cauſed by you and your fore-fathers to be made againſt the Devill and all his works. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preaching and perſwading them, yea, and the ſame people that you engaged to the contrary now, and telling them they muſt now ſinterme of life, what is that but a Popiſh trick and to teach them, <hi>viz.</hi> the people that you engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Devill and all his works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At the enarance into the Covenant of Baptiſm upon ſuch a condition, which now you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to abſolve and teach, to break the condition of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Baptiſm ſo called, and to break the condition of the Covenant, is not that to violate the Covenant and make it void, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſo, whether are not you and the people, that willingly doe ſee the falſe Prophets Ring-leaders of Sects ſince the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, and truce-breakers, or Anti-Chriſtians, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXVI.</head>
                  <p>And if you the pariſh-miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſay theſe things was in the dayes of the late Kings and Biſhops, and are paſt, and not to be heeded now, for the Government is changed, and the Miniſtry being nationall, and not Apoſtolicall or ſpirituall, and according to the Scriptures: but is alterable and changeth as the nationall Government changeth, and therefore couclude, that you are not now accounted the Miniſters of Chriſt, but publick preachers for a nationall maintenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſo, I aske then if you have not the more to anſwer for, and all ſuch: and were you not ſworne to the Common prayer book and that order of worſhip that was in the time of the late Biſhops; if ſo, how can you clear your ſelves in the ſight of God, who have builded people up in thoſe things, if the former be granted, that are accounted by you to be of no uſe, and cryed them up then as the Ordinances of God, and way to the new birth and Covenant of Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concluding formerly that without ſuch things people could not be ſaved? Is it not time for people to look about them, and to beware of the falſe Prophets and Miniſters of Anti-Chriſt? And whether can
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94811:23"/>you truly plead antiquity and ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles about your worſhip, Churches and Ordinances, or Miniſtry in manner and matter according to the Scriptures and the Apoſtolicall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not lie before the Lord and in the ſight of the Son? And whether is your Miniſtry, Ordination and Toleration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Alteration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of any long ſtanding at a certainty, or but within theſe few years, or under the number of twelve, yea or nay?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Are you not offended that the Lord doth diſcover your deeds of darkneſs, and bring people off from your deceits and Popiſh tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the true ſpiritual teachings and worſhip of God againe; and to the Church of which Chriſt Jeſus is head accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, as was before the apoſtacy? and would you not rather have the Saints whipt and ſcourged, or ſent to the houſe of correction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and have the truth ſuppreſt, if you could; and the Church of God perſecuted and ſcattered, if you might have your wills, rather than have unrighteouſneſs and wickedneſs, falſe Miniſters, and the falſe Miniſtry diſcovered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and denied, that truth in its pure appearances may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alted, yea or nay? let that of God in you anſwer, and fleſh or deceit be kept ſilent and under the Croſs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:94811:24"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ANd let all honeſt people and true Chriſtians, who reads this, minde to reade with a right underſtanding, to the end that they may be rightly informed; and ſee if they can yet know who are the falſe Prophets, and if they ſearch the old Laws and Records of the Nation, may they not ſee the riſe, ground, ordination and ſucceſſion of them, in the time of Apoſtacy, to ſpring out, of and from the root of Popery. And may they not ſee the path that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the people, formerly deceived by them, have walked in, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt to the Maſs book, and the like Popiſh Worſhip: And from the Maſs book they aſcended to the Common prayer book, and going backward, they went from the Common prayer book, to the Maſs book againe, and from the Maſs book they aſcended to the Common prayer book again, and ſtood ſtill in it for a time, then the Common prayer book
<pb facs="tcp:94811:24"/>was left, and the Directory took place, and is not ſome, thing elſe preparing inſtead thereof. But now is the Lord teaching by his Spirit, and ſeeking people to the true Spiritual worſhip againe, Joh. 4.23, 24. for ever praiſed be his name.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
